Guide to the Robert Leslie Papers, 1783-1934 and undated, bulk 1814-1872
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Robert Leslie papers 1783-1934 and undated, bulk 1814-1872
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Leslie, Robert, ca. 1794-ca. 1879.
23.7 Linear Feet Approximately 15,398 Items
Merchant, of Petersburg, Va.
Correspondence, accounts, invoices, statements, and legal papers (chiefly 1814-1872) of Leslie, a member of the Virginia mercantile firm of Leslie and Shepherd, and a slave owner. The papers before 1819 largely concern the processing and sale of cotton, tobacco, rice, and western lands. Most of the papers after 1819 pertain to tobacco manufacture in the Richmond-Petersburg area. Other topics include Leslie’s career, family, and travels in England; his western landholdings and efforts to develop the West; his slaveholding and attitude toward it; mercantile prices and U.S.-British trade; and absentee landlordship referring to the maintenance of American property owned by Englishmen. Later material includes scattered correspondence and business papers of Leslie’s nephews, Robert L. Watson and John McGill, whom Leslie had admitted to partnership in the firm.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Robert Leslie papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1950.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, accounts, invoices, statements, and legal papers, chiefly spanning the years 1814-1872, of Robert Leslie, a member of the Virginia mercantile firm of Leslie and Shepherd, and a slave owner. The papers before 1819 largely concern the processing and sale of cotton, tobacco, rice, and western lands. Most of the papers after 1819 pertain to tobacco manufacture in the Richmond-Petersburg area. Other topics include Leslie’s career, family, and travels in England; his western landholdings and efforts to develop the West; his slaveholding and attitude toward it; mercantile prices and U.S.-British trade; and absentee landlordship referring to the maintenance of American property owned by Englishmen. Later material includes scattered correspondence and business papers of Leslie’s nephews, Robert L. Watson and John McGill, whom Leslie had admitted to partnership in the firm.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Absentee landlordism
Commission merchants -- Virginia -- Petersburg
Cotton trade -- Virginia
England -- Description and travel
Great Britain -- Commerce -- United States
Land settlement -- West (U.S.).
Leslie and Shepherd (Petersburg, Va.).
McGill, J. F. (John F.)
Merchants -- Virginia -- Petersburg
Rice trade -- Virginia
Slaveholders -- Virginia
Slavery -- Virginia
Tobacco -- Virginia -- Marketing
United States -- Commerce -- Great Britain
Virginia -- Economic conditions
Watson, Robert L.
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1783-1934, bulk 1814-1872, (35 boxes)
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1783-1815 (Box 1)
  - 1816-1820 (Box 2)
  - 1821-1826 Feb. (Box 3)
  - 1826 Mar.-1827 Apr. (Box 4)
  - 1827 May-1828 Feb. (Box 5)
  - 1828 Mar.-Dec. (Box 6)
  - 1829 Apr.-Sept. (Box 7)
  - 1829 Oct.-1830 Aug. (Box 8)
  - 1830 Sept.-1831 July (Box 9)
  - 1831 Aug.-1832 May (Box 10)
  - 1832 June-1833 Feb. (Box 11)
  - 1833 Mar.-Oct. (Box 12)
  - 1833 Nov.-1834 Apr. (Box 13)
  - 1834 May-Nov. (Box 14)
  - 1834 Dec.-1835 Apr. (Box 15)
  - 1835 May-1835 Oct. (Box 16)
  - 1835 Nov.-1836 June (Box 17)
  - 1836 July-1837 May (Box 18)
  - 1837 June-1838 Feb. (Box 19)
  - 1838 Mar.-Dec. (Box 20)
  - 1839 Jan.-Nov. (Box 21)
  - 1839 Dec.-1840 Sept. (Box 22)
  - 1840 Oct.-1843 Sept. (Box 23)
  - 1843 Oct.-1845 Dec. (Box 24)
  - 1846-1848 (Box 25)
  - 1849 (Box 26)
  - 1850 Jan.-1851 Aug. (Box 27)
  - 1851 Sept.-1853 Apr. (Box 28)
  - 1853 May-1854 Dec. (Box 29)
  - 1855-1857 (Box 30)
  - 1858-1860 Aug. (Box 31)
  - 1860 Sept.-1869 (Box 32)
  - 1860-1872 Sept. (Box 33)
  - 1872 Oct.-1889 (Box 34)
  - 1890-1934 (Box 35)
- Financial Papers Series, 1820s-1899 and undated, (12 boxes)
  - Bills and receipts (Box 36)
    - 1820s
    - 1820s-1830s (Box 37)
    - 1830s (Box 38-41)
    - 1840s (Box 42)
    - 1840s-1850s (Box 43)
    - 1850s (Box 44)
    - 1850s-1860s (Box 45)
    - Undated papers (Box 46-47)
  - Volumes, cashbooks, 1850-1899 (Box 47)
- Addition (1987), (1 box)
  - Chiefly handwritten correspondence. (Box 1)